Finding Aid for Joseph C. Satterthwaite business records, 1844-1872
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph C. Satterthwaite business records 1844-1872
Satterthwaite, Joseph C.
12 oversize volumes
2 linear feet
89250 Aa 2
Business records of J.C. Satterthwaite, primarily of his flour and lumber mill, but also documenting his activities as railroad freight agent and his other business interests in Tecumseh, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by J. N. Satterthwaite and Elizabeth Satterthwaite (donor no. 1242 ), September 1940.
The collection is open to research.
The Satterthwaite family, headed by Samuel Satterthwaite and his son Joseph (J. C.), were proprietors of various mercantile enterprises in the city of Raisin, near Tecumseh, Michigan, during the mid- to late-nineteenth century. Samuel Satterthwaite was the founder of the flour and lumber mills, known as the "Raisin Mills," and established in 1847 and 1838 respectively. His partner in the flour mill was Aaron Comfort, whose surname appears frequently in Satterthwaite's journals and ledgers. Almost nothing is known of his partner in the lumber mill, Tilton Curtis. The name "Raisin Mills" refers to the location of the mills on the River Raisin, one and one-half miles southeast of Tecumseh. Unfortunately, there is no information regarding the warehouse or retail operations which figure prominently in Satterthwaite's collection. In 1864, J.C. Satterthwaite suffered business setbacks due to unpaid debts. Though giving up proprietorship in the mills to another member of the Comfort family, Woolston Comfort, Satterthwaite seems to have continued working there.
The business records in this collection chronicle the commercial and financial transactions of J.C. Satterthwaite and family in the period of 1844-1874 (with the bulk falling in the 1850s and 1860s). Though there are some records prior to the period when Satterthwaite had control of the "Raisin Mills," the great majority of records document the various commercial activities of the Satterthwaite family. Concerned with the routine of daily business life in Raisin and Tecumseh, Michigan, the daily transactions offer a microcosm of small town commerce in nineteenth-century Michigan.
The collection has been arranged by the different kinds of enterprises in which the Satterthwaites were involved: the grain and flour mills, a warehouse (or possibly warehouses), and a retail store. For each of these, Satterthwaite maintained day books, ledgers, and journals. The day books document the daily register/receipts of the grain mill, retail establishment, and warehouse. These volumes encompass the years 1844-1865, with an emphasis on the activity at the grain mill.
The ledgers contain the running documentation of individual customer accounts with an emphasis on accounts established at the warehouse. In addition to ledgers for the grain mill and warehouse, the collection contains two which list railroad freight accounts. These last, seemingly unrelated to any of the other businesses, are presumably evidence of J.C. Satterthwaite's additional career as a railroad freight agent.
The cash books record the cash flow of the various establishments, with, as in the day books, an emphasis on the grain mill transactions. Somewhat unrelated to the rest of the collection is a cash book related to the selling of plaster. Its connection with the other Satterthwaite business records is unclear.
The day books, in particular, offer insight into the bulk quantities of staples purchased by individuals at that time, while that of the retail store reflects other, smaller necessities purchased regularly by the townspeople of Raisin and Tecumseh. The collection concludes with a miscellaneous series consisting of the personal financial documents of J.C. Satterthwaite, coupled with two folders of loan documents and receipts, which together suggest an active borrowing and loaning of funds outside of the confines of the Bank of Tecumseh.
Several volumes in the collection have illegible pages due to their later use as scrapbooks. These scrapbook pages contain contemporaneous newspaper clippings consisting of poetry, caricatures, and inspirational stories.
Subjects:
Business records.; Flour-mills--Michigan--Tecumseh.; J. C. Satterthwaite Grain Mill (Tecumseh, Mich.); Lumbering--Michigan--Tecumseh.; Railroads--Michigan--Tecumseh.; Raisin (Mich.); Tecumseh (Mich.); Satterthwaite, Joseph C.
- Business records
  (bound volumes unless otherwise indicated)
  - Grain Mill
    - Cash Books
      - 1850-1952 (Raisin Mills, Satterthwaite & Comfort) (Box 1)
      - 1853-1856 (Raisin Mills) (Box 1)
      - 1857-1859 (Raisin Mills) (Box 1)
      - 1858-1861 (Volume 1)
    - Day Books
      - 1844-1849 (Volume 2)
      - 1848-1850 (Volume 3)
      - 1850-1852 (Volume 4)
      - 1850-1856 (Volume 5)
      - 1852-1854 (Volume 6)
      - 1856-1857 (Volume 7)
      - 1856-1860 (Volume 8)
      - 1857-1858 (Volume 9)
    - Ledgers
      - 1848-1856 (Volume 1)
      - 1849-1854 (Volume 10)
      - 1849-1856 (Volume 11)
      - 1860 (Volume 12)
  - Plaster
    - Cash Book 1865 (Box 1)
  - Warehouse
    - Cash Books
      - 1851-1853 (Box 1)
      - 1856-1858 (Box 1)
    - Day Books
      - 1855-1858 (Box 1)
      - 1858 (Box 1)
      - 1860-1861 (Box 1)
      - 1861-1862 (Box 1)
      - 1861-1865 (Box 1)
    - Ledgers
      - 1848-1857 (Box 1)
      - 1851-1858 (Box 2)
      - 1853-1855 (Box 2)
      - 1856-1870 (Box 2)
      - 1858-1860 (Box 2)
    - Receipt Book 1846-1850 (Box 2)
  - Retail
    - Day Book 1848-1851 (Box 2)
    - Receipt Book (Satterthwaite & Comfort) 1851-1857 (Box 2)
  - Railroad Freight
    - Ledgers
      - 1851-1854 (Box 2)
      - 1853-1857 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Personal account book undated (Box 2)
    - Bank of Tecumseh bank book undated (Box 2)
    - Cash/expense book 1851-1856 (Box 2)
    - Personal cash book circa 1874 (Box 2)
      (includes diary and address sections)
    - Grist (Order) book circa 1849-1850 (Box 2)
    - Personal loan book circa 1860 (Box 2)
    - Loan Documents, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous letters, land survey, obituary, etc., 1 folders (Box 2)